hello everyone this is Frankie Freitas
and welcome to holotalk the internet's
weekly laser and holography talk show
for the week of November 30th 1998.
we picked up quite a few new listeners
last week mostly due to the topic which
was creating Holograms using a laser
pointer Steve Michael was the guest I'd
like to welcome our new listeners and
hope that you continue with your
interest to the point of actually
setting up your own holography studio
and creating holograms on your own
with this in mind I thought it would be
the perfect week to offer a holography
primer for those listeners who have come
back for more information I went into my
archives of materials and found an audio
tape I recorded several years ago called
the world of holography
covers the history of holography how
lasers work it defines the types and
styles of holograms and looks at where
holography is at present and where it
could be going in the future
I hope you enjoy the presentation and I
received quite a few emails with
questions last week and hopefully this
program will be able to answer many of
them
before we get started Our Guest next
week is going to be Rob Taylor from
fourth dimensional holographics who is
going to fill us in on what's hot with
retail holography this upcoming holiday
season
you're one of the new listeners who is
interested in making Holograms and
selling them you won't want to miss this
show as it will give you some idea as to
what the buying public is looking for
this will be the December 7th show
okay so here is the world of holography
in its entirety I won't be coming on
after the presentation so I will say
thank you for tuning in and don't forget
to tune in each and every week when
whole talk brings you another new show
right on your own computer anywhere in
the world this is Frankie Freitas for
holotalk have a great week
before I begin the actual presentation
segment of this recording I would like
to take a moment to outline the segments
that we'll be following first I would
like to give a brief view of holography
from a historical perspective including
how holography moved from the large
government-funded research facilities
into the obvious environment
moving on from there I would like to
cover the main components of the
practice of making Holograms in the
third segment I will give a breakdown of
the main types and styles of holograms
currently available and their main
similarities and differences
the final segment will cover where
holography is today and where it will be
tomorrow so let us now move into our
first segment holography from a
historical perspective
[Music]
despite the widely held belief that
Holograms are a new technological
innovation the history of holography
actually began in 1948 many years before
the invention of the laser it was at the
Imperial College of London that a
researcher named Dr Dennis Gabor
conceived of and produced the first
hologram the academic paper which he
published entitled image formation by
reconstructed wavefronts went on to earn
him the Nobel Prize in physics in 1971.
Dr Gabor used a carefully filtered
sodium vapor lamp to make his early
Holograms this limited the depth of the
Holograms to only the thickness of a
postage stem but it worked and there was
this history
the actual intent of his research was to
store an image which was illuminated
with very short waves such as X-rays and
then play the image back using very long
waves
in essence this would allow for great
magnifications and Improvement on the
scanning electron microscope which
already could show tremendous detail of
whatever was being imaged it wasn't
until the invention of the laser 12
years later that holography began to
explore the beginnings of its potential
today even 1960 seems like ages ago but
it was the year of the invention of a
device that would create a revolution
of course I am referring to the laser
the word laser is actually an acronym
for the terms light amplification by
stimulated emission of radiation and at
the time of its invention there really
wasn't a use for it
that was a very interesting time in our
history for here we are as a race
creating a tool before anyone had a use
for it it was actually the first time in
human history that this had been so
fact the laser was termed a solution in
search of a problem
but then when researchers hard at work
with the theories of Dennis Gabor at the
time
Yuri danishak of the former Soviet Union
and Emmett Leith and Jewish eupetniks at
the University of Michigan in the United
States
these researchers took abort's theories
applied them using the special
properties of light that only a laser
can produce
and created the first true
three-dimensional images We Now call
Holograms
the scientific journals were absolutely
filled with articles for years after the
initial first Holograms were created it
was actually seen as one of the most
exciting inventions of this century
not only articles and academic papers
but on the legal front literally
hundreds of patents were issued as
Research Laboratories worked not only
around the clock but straight through
the calendar year to come up with uses
for this new technology
as the 60s began to come to a close
corporate interest began to wane
especially at the larger facilities that
were receiving much of the defense
spending on research and development
you have to nearly a decade practical
uses appear to be on the way out
fortunately most of the excitement at
least for the everyday person was just
beginning the Mysteries that were
surrounding the field like a curtain
began to fade away exposing the field to
Millions one of the greatest Revelations
to come out of this transition was the
fact that holography is not necessarily
out of the reach of the amateur or
hobbyists most felt that the field was
too Technical and expensive primarily
because of the fact that it was only
being practiced in larger Research
Laboratories both of these assumptions
were incorrect as far as two technical
is concerned most photographers do not
understand the optical mathematics that
go along with just the simplest camera
there's no reason to expect amateurs
holographers to do so either
basic theory is really all that's needed
here and as far as the course of
equipment is concerned if one has a
basic understanding of the general
theories behind the field a person can
actually make a home holography
laboratory or Stu if you will out of
materials readily available from most
Home Centers and that is exactly what
happened some of these homemade Studios
actually rivaled the larger Laboratories
and quality a few actually surpassed it
and keep in mind the savings of
thousands of dollars off what the larger
Laboratories were paying for equipment
there's no doubt that it was a
revolution it created quite a bit of
noise in the professional circles as
well I mean tell me how do you explain
the person on the other side of town
doing whole grams in their basement that
are actually comparable or even
sometimes better in quality than the
Holograms you've been making on a system
that just cost your company thousands of
dollars it was happening all over and it
is still happening today
there are three major areas of any
holographic setup whether it's a
professional studio laboratory at a
research facility or a Home hobbyist
setup
there is the actual laser the holography
table which contains the lenses and
mirrors used to make the Hologram and
the dark room where the development of
the finished holographic plate takes
place
the laser is a light producing device
that projects a beam of light
a light that is produced by a laser has
very special properties it is these
special properties that allow us to make
a hologram
as of this date today the laser is the
only device that can produce this light
lasers run in size from the size of a
football field are larger but the size
of the grain of salt the common laser
using the field of Photography is the
helium neon laser other lasers are used
as well argon lasers helium cadmium
lasers as well as post Ruby lasers are
also used by some holographers
the diode laser which is a tiny laser
found in many devices such as CD players
are starting to make an appearance in a
few Laboratories for producing Holograms
but as of this state are still in the
research stage
the helium neon laser is used most often
because of a few specific reasons most
recording medium such holographic plates
are produced in large quantities for
this laser it also has the lowest cost
of all the lasers and it has the longest
life with nearly a twenty thousand hour
maintenance free Lifetime on the actual
tube
destruction of the healing and neon
laser consists of a narrow glass tube
similar in appearance to a typical neon
sign that you find in the window of many
delis and pizza shops
the tube is filled with a mixture of the
gases helium and neon and is excited by
using an electrical current flowing
through the tube
this electrical current causes the gases
in the tube to Glow brightly
and each each end of the straight glass
tube mirrors are placed one of the
mirrors is a hundred percent reflective
or it reflects 100 percent of the light
striking it back through the tube again
at the other end of the tube a mirror
which is not quite 100 percent
reflective is placed because this mirror
does not reflect 100 of the light
striking it back through the tube a
small percentage of the light passes
through it
this is the end of the tube that the
actual laser beam exits the laser
because of the shape of the mirrors they
line up the light into a straight line
which is
as a beam
the actual physical construction of a
helium neon laser is quite simple
however it is critical that the
components are at specific distances
from each other especially the mirrors
there
at an exact multiple of the specific
wavefront the laser is producing each
color of the rainbow from red tree
Violet has a specific wavelength it is
the difference in the measurement of the
wavelength that give us the different
colors the helium neon laser produces a
red beam so it is said that it operates
at the rent end of the spectrum the
actual wavelength measurement is stated
in the values which are called
nanometers the exact measurement of the
wavelength that a helium neon laser
produces is
632.8 nanometers or rounded off
633 nanometers
there are lasers which produce several
distinct wavelengths and lasers which
produce only one at a time a helium neon
laser can also be made to produce colors
in both yellow and green parts of the
spectrum but it can only produce one
color at a time this trait of producing
only one color at a time is called
monochromatic common household light
bulbs produce nearly all the colors of
the spectrum and are there for the
furthest things from monochromatic that
you can get
having a monochromatic light source is
an important part of producing a
hologram
the other special property of a laser is
that the light it produces is termed
coherent this is the trait that really
started the ball rolling in holography a
coherent light source has all of the
waves that it produces in line with one
another I like to call it a wave train
wave of light is perfectly in step with
one another for comparison an ordinary
household light bulb is an incoherent
source of light all of the waves that it
produces leave the light bulb in a
random haphazard fashion a good example
that I like to use to help people
visualize this information is I ask them
to picture themselves in a helicopter
stationary over the top of the crowd of
people at an outdoor concert looking
down you see thousands of people you
dressed in different colors and
haphazardly standing around in no
specific well-defined pattern this would
be the light that a household light bulb
would produce
now I ask them to take their helicopter
and hover over the parade marching down
the main street of town
band is moving in unison with one
another marching forward all dressed in
red uniforms this is the light of a
laser one color or monochromatic and
coherent all waves moving along one
right behind the other
I hope this helps you get the picture in
your mind of the difference between
ordinary light and laser light and yes
you can land your helicopter and go have
an ice cream
the next component in any holographic
setup is what is called the holography
table also known as the camera there can
be no vibrations to the system
whatsoever when making a hologram so
special tables must either be
constructed or purchased which absorb
all vibrations before they reach the top
of the table where the Hologram is being
made
the industry term for such a table is a
vibration isolation system the usual
sizes for a table of this type is either
four by four feet or four by eight feet
the tables can be purchased from
scientific supply companies or they can
be built using commonly found materials
from local Home Centers or building
supply companies most purchase systems
are composed of three major components
honeycomb tabletop which has a core of
honeycomb material and a stainless steel
flat top cylinder legs which floats the
massive tabletop on a cushion of air and
an air compressor which slides the legs
with the air for flotation
for high budget government research
these tables are the best that money can
buy but we have to ask ourselves what
did the researchers use before there was
holography in order to invent it
well the answer is they constructed
their own most amateur and hobbyist
philographers build their own tables the
materials are easy to locate and the
cost is very inexpensive compared to a
purchase system from the scientific
supplier
although the actual construction of a
home table system is easy it's beyond
the scope of this tape to go into the
details
[Music]
well now you have a laser and a
vibration isolation table and you're
ready to make Holograms plug in your
laser and you're ready to go you'll
still need a few lenses and mirrors and
of course holographic plates to actually
put the images on there are many
different types of holograms you can
make and I would like to cover a few of
the Styles here with you but before I do
I would like to give my choices for the
instructional books on making Holograms
first the book which I consider the
definitive amateur's guide to making
Holograms is a manual titled the
holography handbook published by Ross
Books in Berkeley California
the second for those of you further into
the field is practical holography
published by Prentice Hall
if you are planning on doing your own
Holograms I want you to be successful
and you cannot go wrong with either of
these books for the Practical advice and
time-tested techniques
as I mentioned before there are many
types of holograms out there I would
like to take a few moments to describe
what it is you are looking at when you
see one I will start with the laser
transmission hologram
laser transmission Holograms are the
granddaddies of all Holograms they
require a laser to make one and also a
laser to view one they are rarely seen
outside the laboratory environment
however and this is very unfortunate if
you ever want to get an idea of exactly
what holography is capable of doing make
or view a laser transmission hologram it
will Astound you
second type of hologram is a white light
transmission hologram these Holograms
require a laser to make them but they
are viewable in ordinary white light
situations such as the Sun or a light
bulb
you may recognize them by the way they
seem to change colors and appear to give
a rainbow effect when viewing them
actually another term for them is
Rainbow Holograms but the laser
transmission hologram and the white
light transmission hologram are viewable
with the source of light passing through
the Hologram from behind it and then
traveling to the viewer's eye
most of the Holograms that are found on
consumer products are white light
transmission Holograms however they have
a silver backing which acts like a
mirror so that when you view them the
light source does not have to travel
through the Hologram but can come from
the same side as the viewer
the silver backing reflects this light
back through the Hologram as if the
light were coming from behind and
traveling through
a very simple ingenious device that
fools the Hologram into thinking that
the light is coming from behind when
actually it is coming from the same side
as the viewer
this leads us to a reflection hologram
reflection hologram replays itself with
the light coming from the same side as
the viewer hence the term reflection it
reflects the light back to the eyes of
the viewer however unlike the silver
backed white light transmission
Holograms with a reflection hologram the
actual hologram reflects the light back
to the viewer not a silver backing
reflection Holograms are easy and fun to
make for the home hobbyist however they
require a bit more stability in your
system than the transmission type of
hologram
another type of hologram that seems to
be making a comeback is the multiplex
hologram also known as a stereogram
these Holograms are actually pieces of
film which are contained in the cylinder
the cylinder rotates and the holographic
image appears to move this movement is
made possible by the fact that the
original image was first recorded onto
standard Motion Picture film and then
transferred in a special way onto the
holographic film
I like to call them sudo Holograms
because of the fact that they were first
shot onto a traditional media such as
movie film and then transferred and made
into a hologram
however the effect is always
entertaining and some very interesting
images have been created in this fashion
some simple types of Multiplex Holograms
can be made at home by the hobbyist but
the commercial quality Multiplex
requires quite a bit of equipment and a
fairly High degree of skill and
knowledge to pull it off
holography at present is being used in a
number of Technical and Artistic
Endeavors automobile manufacturers are
using holography to test their engines
with a technique that is called
holographic interferometry
turbine engines medical implants and
numerous consumer products are tested
this way to see how each reacts under
stress situations
commercial airline pilots are using
holography to view their instrumentation
by projecting it out into space in front
of the aircraft this way they do not
have to take their eyes off the sky to
see the status of their most important
instruments automobile manufacturers
will be including this device known as a
heads-up display in cars in the near
future some cars have it as an option
right now
and we expect to see our friends and
loved ones projected into our homes in
the future the possibility is certainly
there as what is termed real-time
holography is being worked on at such
facilities as the media laboratory at
Massachusetts Institute of Technology
this will allow Holograms to be
transmitted in real time without any
time delay from when the Hologram is
made to when it is viewed
one of the biggest explosions holography
has made to date has been in the graphic
arts industry
Holograms are beginning to appear on a
regular basis on magazine covers
advertisements on consumer packaging and
even on articles of clothing it is a
well-documented fact that including a
hologram on a product or including a
hologram in an advertisement will
increase the consumer's response
the major drawback to most users of
holography were potential users is the
cost Factor set up charges for creating
a hologram to be used in this fashion is
currently cost prohibited for most
however recent advances in creating
holographic Masters which are used to
reproduce the millions of holographic
copies might be moving this cost into an
acceptable range
types of holograms can actually be
produced using a desktop computer and a
specially fitted laser printer at this
point in the game several producers are
experimenting with this method but the
majority of consumer related graphic
arts Holograms are still being produced
in the traditional but costly manner
because of the difficulty reproducing
Holograms many companies have found them
invaluable as a deterrent to
counterfeiters most major credit cards
have holograms on them and the
possibility of including them on U.S
currency is currently being reviewed out
of all the currency in the world the
United States paper is currently near
the top of the list when it comes to
ease of reproduction recently in a major
County feeding operation was closed
which was producing counterfeit
Holograms but as far as we know this was
an isolated incident Holograms are still
by far the best insurance against
counterfeiters known today
as the world continues to discover the
magic of holography and as more and more
applications which seem like science
fiction only a few years ago become
reality we will continue little by
little to view the standards of Imaging
which we feel is so high-tech and
advanced with less and less excitement
the day will come when it will seem
almost primitive to see an image which
does not appear three-dimensionally in
front of us the widescreen high
definition digital TVs which give which
give such an astounding picture of the
world around us will suddenly seem flat
and missing something
they will be sold or taken up to the
resting place in the Attic while we
actively enjoy beautiful blue color
three-dimensional concerts sporting
events and yes even romantic Rendezvous
which would be so lifelike that not only
will it seem like we're there we
actually will be
I am happy for your forward and future
mindedness with your interest in the
field of holography for me it has been
literally a lifetime of Adventure and
discovery
I hope you stay with us on this journey
will be long and rewarding and I hope
you're still with us when we move into
that promised day and age when we can
look back and say that we will all
Pioneers in this headstrong field we've
come to call holography